## **ADAM RULE**

Oregon Health & Science University 3181 S.W. Sam Jackson Park Rd, Mail Code: BICC Portland, OR 97239-3098 rulea@ohsu.edu adamrule.com

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

Human-Computer Interaction, Data Science, Computational Notebooks, Cognitive Science, Medical Informatics, Electronic Medical Records

My research focuses on the design and use of software supporting data analysis. I aim to make interactive systems that encourage analytical and collaborative best practices so that analyses are lucid, reproducible, and sound.

### **EDUCATION**

2013 - 2018 University of California, San Diego

PHD, *Cognitive Science* Advisor: Jim Hollan

Committee: Gloria Mark, Brad Voytek, Bill Griswold, Philiip Guo, Rob El-Kareh

2011 - 2013 University of Washington, Seattle

MS, Human Centered Design & Engineering

2008 - 2011 University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign

BS, Industrial Engineering — Highest Honors

#### CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

- C4 Adam Rule, Aurélien Tabard, Jim Hollan. Exploration and Explanation in Computational Notebooks. *In Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI)*, 2018 HONORABLE MENTION, TOP 5% OF SUBMISSIONS
- C3 Adam Rule, Steven Rick, Michael Chiu, Phillip Rios, Shazia Ashfaq, Alan Calvitti, Wesley Chan, Nadir Weibel, Zia Agha. Validating free-text order entry for a notecentric EHR. *In Proceedings of the American Medical Informatics Association Annual Meeting (AMIA)*, 2015
- C2 Adam Rule, Aurélien Tabard, Karen Boyd, Jim Hollan. Restoring the Context of Interrupted Work with Desktop Thumbnails. *In Proceedings of the Cognitive Science Society Annual Meeting (CogSci)*, 2015
- C1 **Adam Rule**, Jodi Forlizzi. Designing interfaces for multi-user, multi-robot systems. *In Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Robot Interaction (HRI)*, 2012 HONORABLE MENTION, TOP 5% OF SUBMISSIONS

#### JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- J4 Michelle Hribar, Adam Rule, Abigail Huang, Austin Igelman, Bradley Henriksen, Haley Dusek, Isaac Goldstein, Michael Chiang, Wei-Chun Lin. Redundancy of Progress Notes for Serial Office Visits. Ophthalmology, (In Press) 2019
- J3 Adam Rule, Amanda Birmingham, Cristal Zuniga, Ilkay Altintas, Shih-Cheng Huang, Rob Knight, Niema Moshiri, Mai H. Nguyen, Sara Brin Rosenthal, Fernando Pérez, Peter W. Rose. Ten Simple Rules for Writing and Sharing Computational Analyses in Jupyter Notebooks. PLoS Computational Biology, 15(7): e1007007, 2019
- J2 Adam Rule, Ian Drosos, Aurélien Tabard, Jim Hollan. Aiding Collaborative Reuse of Computational Notebooks with Annotated Cell Folding. *Proceedings of the ACM Human-Computer Interaction*, 1(CSCW), 2018
- J1 Adam Rule, Aurélien Tabard, Jim Hollan. Using Visual Histories to Reconstruct the Mental Context of Suspended Activities. *Human-Computer Interaction*, 32(5-6), 2017

## **DOCTORAL CONSORTIUM, WORKSHOP & POSTER PUBLICATIONS**

- W1 Adam Rule, Aurélien Tabard, Jim Hollan. Traces: A Flexible, Open Source Activity Tracker for Workplace Studies. *Workshop on the Quantified Workplace at the ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW)*, 2017
- P3 **Adam Rule**, Erin Gillespie, Nadir Weibel, Todd Pawlicki. Design Thinking in Radiation Oncology. *Human Factors and Ergonomics Society Healthcare Symposium*, 2016
- P2 Adam Rule, Aurélien Tabard, Jim Hollan. Thinking in 4D: Preserving and Sharing Mental Context Across Time. *In Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing Companion (CSCW)*, 2016
- P1 Karen Boyd, **Adam Rule**, Aurélien Tabard, Jim Hollan . Human Values in Tracking and Sharing Computer-Mediated Activity at Work. In Proceedings of the *ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing Companion (CSCW)*, 2016
- D1 **Adam Rule**. Visualizing Computer Activity to Support the Resumption of Long-term Creative Work. *In Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Creativity & Cognition*, 2015

## DISSERTATION

2018 The Design and Use of Computational Notebooks Adam Rule Cognitive Science, UC San Diego

### **MENTORING & ADVISING**

2019-Present OREGON HEALTH & SCIENCE UNIVERSITY Haley Dusek (MD)
Jimmy Chen (MD)

Michael Aaby (BS)

2013 - 2018 UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO

Azeem Ghumman (MS Thesis) — Software Engineer @ Zoox Rizwan Ahmad (MS Thesis) — Sr Software Engineer @ Notebowl Jonas Kemper (MS) — Software Engineer @ McKinsey Dig. Labs Kendall Youngstrom (BS Thesis) — UX Researcher @ Google

Ram Dixit (BS Thesis) ——MS Student @ University of Texas, Houston

Karen Boyd (BS) — PhD Student @ University of Maryland Adam Powers (BS) — Information Developer @ Tealium

Regina Cheng (BS) — PhD Student @ University of Washington

Nathan Hassanzadeh (BS)

Katya Noble (BS) — UX Design Intern @ Axos Bank Allison Reiss (BS) — Software Engineer @ Kiran Analytics

Evan Schmitz (BS) — UX Researcher @ Microsoft

#### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

Summer 2019 BMI 510 — Human Computer Interaction in Biomedicine

Mentored Teaching with Michelle Hribar and Michael Chiang

Spring 2018 COGS 10 — Cognitive Consequences of Technology

Teaching Assistant with Jim Hollan

Winter 2017 DSGN 1 — Design of Everyday Things

Teaching Assistant with Jim Hollan

Winter 2016 COGS 120 — HCI Design - Outstanding Teaching Award

Teaching Assistant with Scott Klemmer

Winter 2015 COGS 102b — Cognitive Ethnography

Teaching Assistant with Melanie McComsey

Spring 2014 COGS 102c — Cognitive Design Studio

Teaching Assistant with Jim Hollan

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2019 - Present Oregon Health & Science University

Postdoctoral Scholar

Advisors: Michael Chiang, Michelle Hribar

Researching design and use of electronic health records

2013-2018 University of California San Diego, Design Lab

Research Assistant Advisors: Jim Hollan

Researched design and use of computational notebooks and electronic health records

Summer 2012 Amazon

UX Research Intern

Conducted usability studies on shopping interfaces for clothing and home goods

Summer 2012 PATH

UX Research Intern

Evaluated usability of inventory software for medical equipment

Fall 2011 University of Washington, CHILL Lab

Directed Research Group

Conducted interviews informing design of BabySteps development tracking app

Summer 2011 Carnegie Mellon University, QoLT Center

Research Intern

Conducted research on the design of interfaces for controlling robot teams

Summer 2010 Intel Research

User Research Intern

Conducted research on the design of home assistive robot

## SERVICE, AWARDS, HONORS

REVIEWING

CHI (2016,19), CSCW (2019), IUI (2019), AMIA (2015,16,19), Ophthalmology (2019), Applied Clinical Informatics (2019)

OTHER SERVICE

2019 AMIA Student Paper Competition Committee

AWARDS

2018 Honorable Mention, CHI 2018 — top 5% of all submissions

2016 Outstanding Teaching Award, Cognitive Science Department, Winter 2016

2012 Honorable Mention, HRI 2012 — top 5% of all submissions

2012 Microsoft Design Expo — Best Presentation

**FELLOWSHIPS** 

2019 - 2020 National Library of Medicine Postdoctoral Training Grant

2014 - 2017 National Library of Medicine Predoctoral Training Grant — 3 years tuition & stipend

### **INVITED TALKS**

Composition of Clinical Documentation

Oregon Health & Science University, Casey Eye Institute, June 2019

The Design and Use of Computational Notebooks

University of Washington, Interactive Data Lab, Dec 2018

Oregon Health & Science University, Medical Informatics, Nov 2018

Field Methods in Human Computer Interaction

Guest Lecture, COGS 13 (Field Methods) UC San Diego, May 2018

**Exploration and Explanation in Computational Notebooks** 

UC Berkeley, Data Science Institute, Dec 2017

Cognitive Science & Design

Guest Lecture, COGS 1 (Intro to Cognitive Science) UC San Diego, Nov 2016 Guest Lecture, COGS 1 (Intro to Cognitive Science) UC San Diego, Oct 2015